<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The troubles of Geneua VVith the warres which the Duke of Sauoy hath made against it these three yeeres space. And the great victories which God hath lately giuen to the citizens of Geneua. Trulie translated according to the French copie. by W.P. The map of Geneua.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11727</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838777</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838777</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3165</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 639:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The troubles of Geneua VVith the warres which the Duke of Sauoy hath made against it these three yeeres space. And the great victories which God hath lately giuen to the citizens of Geneua. Trulie translated according to the French copie. by W.P. The map of Geneua.</title>
                  <author>Phillip, William, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>W. P., fl. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas Scarlet] for Thomas Nelson, and are to be sold at his shop at the great south doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.P. = William Phillip.</note>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>With a title page map.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed "Tho. Nelson". Variant: dedication signed "T.N.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles Emmanuel --  I, --  Duke of Savoy, 1562-1630.</term>
               <term>Geneva (Switzerland) --  History --  1536-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3165:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3165:1"/>
            <p>The troubles of Geneua.</p>
            <p>With the warres which the Duke of Sauoy hath made againſt it theſe three yeeres ſpace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the great victories which God hath lately giuen to the Citizens of Geneua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Trulie tranſlated according to the French copie. <hi>by W. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of Geneva and surroundings</figDesc>
               <head>The Map of Geneua.</head>
               <p>GENEVA</p>
               <p>LEMAN-LAKE</p>
               <p>THONON</p>
               <p>BALIADGE DE GEZ</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Thomas Nelſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the great South doore of Paules. 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3165:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3165:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE Lordes of her Highneſſe moſt <hi>Honorable Priuie Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a thing of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie great conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) to behold The Woonderfull worke of almightie God, in strengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge thoſe that continuallie fight for the defence of the true &amp; ſincere Religion of Chriſt Ieſus: as hath beene ſeene within this Iſland, which in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon to the worlde, is but as a handfull: yet is the ſame ſo defended (by the prouidence of almightie God) from ſpoiling &amp; ſubuerting, that neither forrain practiſes abroad, nor ciuil diſcord, or priuy pretended treaſons at home, or the inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the mightieſt enemie can once preuaile againſt it: as hath of
<pb facs="tcp:3165:3"/>
late yeares bene manifeſted, to the great amazement, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, and confuſion of the chiefeſt complotters of ſuch bad actions. And this (right Honorable) is not ſeene onely in this Iſland, but generallie euen in all Nations, Cities, or Townes, where Gods truth is aduanced, preached, &amp; preferred before Idolatrie and ſuperſtition: as appeareth by that famous City of <hi>Geneua,</hi> where God is rightlie honoured, and his worde ſincerelie preached. Of which Cittie, (right Honourable) this diſcourſe enſuing trulie deſcribeth, and aſwell laieth open their troubles, ſuſtained by the inuaſion of the Duke of Sauoy and his forces, for the time of theſe three years, as alſo the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels and vnlooked for victories which almightie God hath giuen the Cittizens of <hi>Geneua,</hi> againſt the Sauoyans theyr deadlie enemies: Thus preſenting the ſaide diſcourſe vnto your Honours, beeing trulie publiſhed in the Engliſh tongue, according to the French Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, I humblie take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt humble <hi>T. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3165:3"/>
            <head>¶The deſcription of the Towne of Geneua, with the troubles that happened therevnto by warres which the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> made againſt the ſaid Towne, from the beginning of the yere 1589. vntill this yeere 1591.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eneua</hi> is a moſt ancient Citie, lying between the Countries of <hi>Sauoy</hi> and <hi>Swiſerland,</hi> whereof <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the beginning of his Commentaries maketh mention: which towne euer ſince hath (by the prouidence of God) bin preſerued and defended from all dangers, euen in the midſt of all the wars and troubleſome times, which vntill this latter age haue happened in many Countries enuironing the ſame, and now of late hauing receiued the reformation of the Goſpell, it hath beene more renowmed then euer it was, by diuerſe meruailous actions &amp; euents, which the Almightie God hath ſhewen in the defence and conſeruation of the ſame. It hath for a long time ben a free imperiall Citie, ſcituated at the ende of one of the moſt great and notable Lake in the world, called <hi>Leman-lake,</hi> in bredth at the largeſt part, eight Engliſh miles, and extendeth in length thirtie or two and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:3165:4"/>
mile, which Lake aboundeth in great ſtore of fiſh, and is verie commodious for all the Countrie, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the traffique vppon the ſame, ſpecially for the carriage of their woods which they fetch from of the mountaines. This Lake ſerueth in place of a rampire vnto the Towne on the North ſide thereof. On the Eaſt part it hath the balliages of <hi>Thonon,</hi> of <hi>Chablais</hi> &amp; the Countrie of Foſſigny, within two, three, foure and fiue leagues of the gates, which Countries are borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with great and high hils, being enuironed with the Alpes. On the South part there is a moſt fertil &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant hill named <hi>Saleue,</hi> at the foote whereof lieth the balliage of <hi>Ternier,</hi> in a moſt rich and goodly plaine, extending in length three leagues, and in bredth two leagues, which balliage is bordered on the South part with the riuer of <hi>Rhoſne,</hi> and on the North parte with the riuer of <hi>Arue,</hi> little more than a quarter of a league diſtant from <hi>Geneua,</hi> and lieth at the foot of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of <hi>Wache,</hi> which runneth a long by the end of the towne, ſeparating the ſame by a bridge from Saint <hi>Geruais,</hi> a borough verie well fortified and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. On the one ſide of the riuer of <hi>Rhoſne</hi> towardes the South lieth the balliage of <hi>Gez,</hi> containing in length foure leagues, and in breadth two leagues, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed with the mountaine of <hi>Iura,</hi> on the further ſide of which mountain lieth the Franche Counte. At the one end whereof is the towne and caſtle of <hi>Gez,</hi> two great leagues diſtant from <hi>Geneua.</hi> At the other end to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Lions</hi> is the ſtraight and narow paſſage of the <hi>Cluſe,</hi> a place both by arte and nature verie ſtrong, ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated betweene two mountaines and the riuer of <hi>Rhoſne. Thonon</hi> is fiue leagues diſtant from <hi>Geneua,</hi> lieng
<pb facs="tcp:3165:4"/>
vpon the Lacque, extending it ſelfe towards the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>Valois,</hi> in ſuch manner that <hi>Geneua</hi> is found to be enuironed with the three balliages aforeſayd, which vpon certain conditions were reſtored vnto the Duke of Sauoy by the Lordes of Berne in the yere 1567.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of Geneva and surroundings</figDesc>
               <head>The deſcription of Geneua.</head>
               <p>GENEVA</p>
               <p>LEMAN-LAKE</p>
               <p>THONON</p>
               <p>BALLADGE DE GEZ</p>
            </figure>
            <p>In theſe three balliages (the territories of the Lordſhip of <hi>Geneua</hi> being comprehended) which are incloſed within the ſame, there hath in times part beene almoſt 300. good villages, beſides the hamlets and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſtanding ſcattered in diuerſe places, barnes, and a great number of Caſtles, whereof more then the halfe of them haue bene burnt, deſtroyed, and ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb facs="tcp:3165:5"/>
in theſe laſt warres. Part whereof are herevnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed.</p>
            <p>Long time ſince, as it were naturally, and by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, from the Father vnto the ſonne, the Dukes &amp; Earles of <hi>Sauoy</hi> haue vſed many meanes, and ſought di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe occaſions both by practiſes and violence, to make themſelues Lords of the towne of <hi>Geneua,</hi> the moſt faire and greateſt Citie (whatſoeuer) in thoſe partes, and is the key, whereby (if they coulde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the ſame) they might enter into <hi>Switſerland.</hi> The Duke laſt deceaſed, hauing obtained the three ballia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aforeſayd, during the time of his life, did greatlie moleſt and trouble (although verie ſubtilly) the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Geneua,</hi> yet not minding to enter into an open warre with the ſayd towne, the diſcommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whereof he had otherwiſe oftentimes aſſaied and experimented. But <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> his ſonne, not long after his entrie into the eſtate of the Dutchie of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> did preſently diſcouer and make knowen his euill wil and hatred vnto the ſayde Citie of <hi>Geneua,</hi> by ſeeking to ſurpriſe the ſame in the yeere 1582. and at that time ſhewed his forces before it, threatning them with a greate armie, vnder the conduct of the Earle of <hi>Raco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Piamontois.</hi> Not long time after hauing eſpouſed Ladie <hi>Katherine,</hi> the yongeſt daughter of the king of Spaine, he tooke a further matter in hand, that was, to inuade all the Countrie lying about the Lake of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> which appertaineth vnto the Canton of Berne, thinking by that means in ſhort time to become Lord of <hi>Geneua,</hi> which Towne in the meane time did not ceaſe to be much moleſted and troubled, not onely by his foragers, exactors, and commiſſaries, but alſo to
<pb facs="tcp:3165:5"/>
be ſolicited and tempted by diuerſe means, both with faire promiſes and threatnings. To the which end he had appointed <hi>Francis Melchior de Saint Ioire,</hi> Baron of Ermaus, with other his adherents, that they ſhould ſecretly practiſe in the Countrie of Vaut, the winning and taking (at a certaine daie appointed) of the caſtles of <hi>Chillon, Veuay, Lauſanne, Morges</hi> and <hi>Nion,</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall places ſcituated about the Lake. Hee had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made a view and muſter of all his forces, and had alreadie cauſed a part thereof to paſſe the mountains. Hee helde a great gariſon within the Caſtle of <hi>Gez,</hi> as alſo in the countrie of <hi>Cluſe,</hi> and the caſtle of <hi>Thonon.</hi> And within the forte of <hi>Ripaille</hi> about a quarter of a league from <hi>Thonon,</hi> he kept a garriſon of fiue hundred Piemontois, men purpoſely choſen out, where he had likewiſe two gallies, great &amp; ſufficient inough to hold two hundreth men in each gallie beſides their furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which were readie at all times to be lanched into the Lake if occaſion ſhould ſerue. During theſe prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, the Duke fell in hand with another enterpriſe, in the moneth of October 1588. vſurping vpon (the crowne of <hi>France</hi>) the Marquiſate of <hi>Saluſſes</hi> in <hi>Pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont:</hi> which in ſhort time hauing brought to effect by meanes of the intelligences hee had within the ſame, hee cauſed his pretence to bee put in practiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtates of <hi>Berne</hi> and <hi>Geneua,</hi> who in the meane time continued verie peaceable and quiet, although <hi>Geneua</hi> indured great iniurie by meanes that the traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique and victuals were hindered and kept from it. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this occaſion the French king, <hi>Henrie</hi> the 3. being moued with the vſurpation of his Marquiſate, by his Ambaſſadors ſolicited the Seigniors of <hi>Berne</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3165:6"/>
together with ſome of the Cantons of Switſers, the Valoiſons and Griſons, to aide and aſſiſt him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> by whom he alleadged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be vniuſtly aſſailed and deſpoiled. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion was, to inuade thoſe countries which he held about <hi>Geneua,</hi> meane time that the king ſhoulde giue him ſomewhat to doe out of Daulphinois. This reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution finiſhed, on wedneſdaie the ſecond of Aprill 1589. the horſe and footmen of <hi>Geneua</hi> iſſued forth, and marching towards <hi>Foſsigny</hi> wanne the Caſtle of Monthou, &amp; a little towne called Bonne, brake down certaine bridges vpon the riuer of <hi>Arue,</hi> and marched as farre as Saint <hi>Ioire,</hi> a caſtle belonging vnto the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Ermanſſe,</hi> wherein they found (and ſent them to <hi>Geneua</hi>) all the papers, remembrances, letters and commiſſions of the Duke of Sauoy and of his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officers, concerning the ſecret enterpriſes deuiſed againſt the ſtates of Berne and Geneua. Theſe troups conducted and lead by Monſieur <hi>de Quirry,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of France, and knight of the order, turning their courſe the monday following, marched on the other ſide, wanne the town and caſtle of Gez, together with all the balliage: and hauing aſſaied (although in vain) to force the paſſage of Cluſe, returned with their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie vnto Geneua, being in number aboue nine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, whereof the moſt part were footmen.</p>
            <p>Theſe exploits cauſed a great rumor and meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous aſtoniſhment in all the Country of Sauoy, which the Duke himſelfe and his ſecret friends reioyced at, ſaying, that the occaſion by him &amp; his ſo many times ſought and procured, did now voluntarily offer and pres;ent it ſelfe vnto them. Which hee neglected not,
<pb facs="tcp:3165:6"/>
but with great diligence imbraced the ſame, as by the gathering of his forces (which in few daies after he had prepared and made readie) eaſily appeared: for that the French Kings armie entering into the paſſage of Thonon, hauing taken the towne, which is not verie ſtrong, and the caſtle yeelded by compoſition, layde ſiege vnto the fort of Ripaille. The Countie of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineugue,</hi> with the baſtard of Sauoy, reſolued to raiſe the ſiege, hauing gathered aboue twelue hundreth lances, fiue hundreth Argolettiers, and about fifteene hundreth foot men, marched ouer the mountaines, and did ſo much, that on tewſdaie the nine and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith of Aprill, they deſcended without reſiſtaunce, within the countrie, verie neere vnto the Towne of Thonon, from whence (after a few skirmiſhes &amp; char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges giuen on both ſides) the Countie <hi>Martineugue</hi> being wounded, they retired to their ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, without ſuccouring or deliuering the aſſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged within Ripaille, who hauing greater want of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage then of victualls, or of good meanes to defend &amp; keepe the place, not long after yeelded it vp, their liues and goods ſaued, leauing the two gallies behind them, which with two frigats (other kinde of veſſels for the water) were burnt, and the fort deſtroyed and layd waſt. That done, they marched into the Countrie of Foſſigny, which the Duke of Sauoy vnderſtanding, cauſed part of his forces, as well horſe as footmen, to make haſt thether, to keep the paſſage, which country of Foſſigny is a territory or Lordſhip comprehending about ten or twelue leagues (as well mountaines as plaine ground) in breadth and length, and beginneth about the towne of Bonne, hauing the Alpes on the
<pb facs="tcp:3165:7"/>
Eaſt part, the Countie of <hi>Geneua</hi> on the South part, &amp; <hi>Geneua</hi> it ſelfe within three leagues: The Lake on the weſt part, &amp; <hi>Thonon</hi> with the Country of <hi>Vaut</hi> on the north part. The winning of this countrey gaue an entrie vnto theſe of <hi>Geneua</hi> to paſſe further: and is a verie ſtrong keie or paſſage into <hi>Sauoye.</hi> The balliage, of <hi>Chablois, Boige,</hi> with other places adioyning. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thoſe of <hi>Geneua</hi> holde the towne of <hi>Bonne,</hi> which is as it were the gate or entrie of the ſame. Meane time, the Barron of <hi>Ermanſſe,</hi> which not long before, had by compoſition recouered his Caſtell of Saint <hi>Ioire,</hi> knowing of what importaunce the ſaid place (beeing within two leagues of the towne of <hi>Bonne,</hi> and ſo farre within the mountaines) was vnto all the Countrey, cauſed a forte or skonſe of earth to be made vpon the mount of Caſtels, betweene the high mountaines of <hi>Maule,</hi> &amp; thoſe of <hi>View,</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſtaux,</hi> placing in the ſame a companie of Piemontiſians, vnder the which fort, he raiſed a platforme of earth, wheron he placed foure field peeces, each peece bearing a Bullet of the bignes of an egge. On the further ſide thereof vpon the way going to ſaint <hi>Ioire,</hi> he made a Barricado, and vnder in the way, leading from <hi>Vieu</hi> vnto ſaint <hi>Ioire,</hi> not far from a barne called <hi>Warnoz,</hi> an other ſtrong Barrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, kept by a company of Harquebuſiers of Fosſignie. The reſt of the Countrey being ſtraight, narrow, and difficult to be entred, might eaſilie bee defended and kept by very ſmall force againſt a puiſſant armie. This notwithſtanding, the Baron did ſo much, that beſides the companies, aſwell of horſe as foote men, wherof he had ſufficient to defend the Country, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured an aide of 500. Launces to bee ſent vnto him,
<pb facs="tcp:3165:7"/>
which were paid by the townes and Contrey of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, &amp; conducted by the Counteſſe of Valpergue, and S. Martin: wherewith he being ioyned, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined (truſting vnto the fort aforſayd, and of their foot companies, which they might eaſily place in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcado betweene the Barne of Warnoz and the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of Latour,) to ſhew themſelues in the field which lieth betweene that village, and the Caſtell of Tyer: hoping of two thinges, that one woulde take effect, which was, either that the armie of Berne, conſiſting of thirtie eight or 40. Enſignes approching, might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie be ouerthrowen by them, (for they eſtemed not of the companies of Geneua) or els, hauing feared &amp; aſtoniſhed that armie, they ſhould conſtraine it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire. So that on ſaterday, the 16. of Iuly 1589. they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incamped in the field, betweene their fort and the Caſtell of Tier, (the armie of Berne lying at Pillonay, about halfe a league from that place.) They deuided their horſe into 3. Squadrons, a bow ſhot diſtant one from the other: The laſt of their troopes being in the houſes of the village of Latour, and the firſt part neere vnto the ſaid houſes among the brackes. The Lanciers of Piemont were in two other Squadrons, at the end of the three firſt Squadrons: there was likewiſe a ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Argolitiers of Foſſigny, conducted by the Baron of <hi>Ermanſſe,</hi> which made a halt couertlie vnder the trees and houſes of the villages of Latour: part of their footmen were ſet in diuers places for their moſt aduantage. The Lord <hi>Vateuille Auoier,</hi> Generall of the armie of Berne, conſidering and beholding the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and maner of the Sauoyans, cauſed all his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to be raunged in order of battell, betweene <hi>Pillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3165:8"/>
and Vieu, chooſing out of the ſame three com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Harguebuſiers and Musketiers, vnder the leading of Captaine Berole, Boſſey, and N. with the number of twentie Argoletiers or thereabouts, and a companie of harguebuſes of Geneua, lead by captain Iaques, to march forwards, which made the point, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeconded by the ſhot of Boiſioli, he therewith ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the Sauoyans footmen to forſake their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcado, and Boiſioli at that inſtant ceazed vppon the caſtle of Tier. On the other ſide captaine Guinet with one hundred ſhot taking the lower waie, ſodainly ſet vpon the baricado of the horſe of Warnoz, where he ſlew all ſuch of the Foſſigniers as reſiſted him, and put the reſt vnto flight. Captaine Iaques with his bands, following likewiſe after the companies of foot, which had left their ambuſcado vnder a hedge. The Duke of Sauoyes horſemen perceiuing that, began to retire, which the horſemen of Geneua (beeing placed in the ſide waie betweene Vieu and Tier) being deſcended into the plaine field, and perceiuing the Dukes foote men to flie, trauerſed forcibly among the Dukes horſe which becauſe they were incloſed on each ſide within a ſtraight and narow lane, neere vnto the village of la Touer, had neither time nor leaſure to turne their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo that of al their troups there was not aboue three rankes, which couched their lances againſt the enimy, into one of the which captain Bois (lieuetenant to the Lord of Varro, Colonell of the horſes of Geneua) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, where being hurt in the mouth, he was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to turne on the left hand, but he was ſo wel ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by 120. lances and fiftie argoletiers, with certaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies of footmen, that the Countes of Valpergne
<pb facs="tcp:3165:8"/>
and of S. Martin, with the greateſt part of the Piemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toiſians horſes, hauing receiued the ouerthrowe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained dead vpon the place, the reſt being ſcattered fled in great diſorder vnto the top of the mountaine, whereas many of them were loſt, the reſt with great danger ſaued themſelues within Bonne ville &amp; other places of Foſſignie: which the Dukes footmen percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, forſooke their fort and fled into the mountains, but the Baron of Ermanſſe with his Argolettiers ſaued themſelues with the firſt, not once offering to fight, by which means the honor of the field, together with the fort, the foure field peeces, &amp; all the barricados remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the companies of Berne and Geneua. The Duke loſt at that time almoſt 300. horſe and foot, &amp; the Bernors not aboue fiue men at the moſt, whereof cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Bois was one, who not long after died of the wound receiued in his mouth, beeing verie much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for his valor and prowes. Which done (thoſe of Berne hauing the field, yeelded thankes vnto God for their great victorie) the Generall Vateuille cauſed the armie to march towards Saint Ioire, whereas the caſtle within few daies after yeelded by compoſition, which they burnt. Vntill that time the affaires of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua ſeemed to proſper and go forwards: but not long after the Switſers and Griſons changed their courſe, &amp; marched toward France by the waie of New caſtle, &amp; the Franche Counte, by which meanes Geneua itſelf was forced to ſuſtaine the whole charge and burthen of the wars, wherwith the Duke of Sauoy being verie wel pleaſed, thought therby to attain vnto the effect of his deſires, he failed not to approch nere Geneua with a puiſſant armie, conſiſting of more then 16. thouſand, and great ſtore of ordinaunce for batterie: his Vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard
<pb facs="tcp:3165:9"/>
hauing done certaine ſmale exploytes in the Countrey of Foſſigny, ſo that about the beginning of the moneth of Iune, he entred into the balliage of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier, whereas with his Canon ſhot he battered an old towne, the ſouldiers whereof in number about fortie or fiftie, being readie to yeeld the ſame vnto him, hee promiſed to ſaue their liues, but hauing entered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto his faith and promiſe, he cauſed them all to be hanged. From thence, to the end he might aſtoniſh thoſe of Geneua, and ſo conſtraine them forcibly with all humilitie to yeeld vnto him, when they ſhould ſee ſo puiſſant an enemie, with thirtie canon ſhot vnder their wals, hee enterpriſed to batter a little mount of earth, which they in great haſt had raiſed by the bridge of Arue, whereas fiue times one after the other he gaue the aſſault, but to his ſhame and diſhonour, both he and his army were repulſed and driuen backe, with the loſſe of many of his valianteſt ſouldiers, which tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was done more by Gods hand then by the force &amp; induſtrie of thoſe of Geneua, which had theerin but a verie ſmall number of men, and thoſe fighting onely by handfulls and without order, yet with an incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courage and boldnes, and with an extraordinarie ſucceſſe and euent. He ſeeing himſelfe to receiue ſuch a repulſe, tooke another courſe, &amp; after certaine ſmall exploits went &amp; aſſieged the towne of Bonne in Foſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigny, wherin lay three companies of Geneua, which yelded vnto him by compoſition: but the ſame was as well kept with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it was with thoſe of Ternier, for that the Duke at their iſſuing forth cauſed them all to be cut in peeces. This done, he recouered the caſtle of Thonon, from whence he marched with all his forces vnto the country of Cluſe, a Countrie ſcituated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb facs="tcp:3165:9"/>
two hils neere vnto the riuer of Rhoſne, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Duke held a fort named the Cluſe, the ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof is as followeth.</p>
            <p>Mount Iura being about foure or fiue daies iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to trauell out-right, beginneth in the Weſt about foure leagues diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Geneua, ſtretching towards Lions. At the place where it endeth, there lieth right againſt it in the South the mountaine of Wache, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the which two ends of hills (as neere one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other, as a musket ſhotte) the famous riuer of Rhoſne hath her courſe, which by diuerſe turnings &amp; windings runneth vnto Lions. Farther within at the foote of mount Iura, it is bordered and proſpected with an high hill named <hi>Creſdo</hi> (a worde ſignifieng, a mount of earth raiſed on high) vnder the which lieth a little plaine aboute halfe a quarter of a league in breadth, at the ende whereof there is a village called Longeray. Paſſing along the rocke or ſtones of this mount Iura, about the end thereof there is a ſtraight and narow waie, winding in forme of a ſerpent, vpon the which a cart may verie well paſſe, and by reaſon of the ſteepnes of the ſame, hauing the riuer of Rhoſne verie ſwiftly running at the foot thereof, is verie eaſie to be kept. In the midſt thereof, which is about two musket ſhot in length, there ſtandeth a fort, part wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is by maine force cut out of the rock it ſelfe, the reſt builded of hard ſtones, ſpecially on that ſide which butteth vpon Geneua, and halfe couered with earth, in manner of a wall, about the length of eighteene or twentie paces towards Geneua, all the foot of this fort (before that time being hollow, and ſeruing for a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage vnto carts &amp; horſes) was filled with earth, &amp; that horſe &amp; men might pas. There is a draw bridge made
<pb facs="tcp:3165:10"/>
which commeth out of the Fort, and ſtretcheth along by the ſame, which although it ſhould be taken by the enemie, doth not any thing at all hinder the ſayd fort, but might eaſilie be wone againe, by reaſon that it can not be held but by thoſe within the Fort, not poſſible to be ſcaled, wherein you maie not enter, but one by one, and that verie hardly. Within this Fort, partly out of the Rocke, and partlie builded of free ſtones, there are lodgings for a Captaine and about 60. Souldiers, with certaine places for their prouiſions. On that ſide which butteth vpon Le-Vache and Longeray, it lieth more open and diſcouered, &amp; is eaſier to be battered: but very difficultly vpon Geneua ſide, by reſon the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillary may not be placed nearer then within 100. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the ſame: although that they of Geneua, about the moneth of April, in the yere of our Lord 1589. did aſſay with their Canon to batter the ſame. This Forte the Duke minding to fortifie, and make it of greater ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, cauſed another fort to be made, naming it the litle Cluſe, being on the other ſide of the riuer of Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſne ouer againſt the place where thoſe of Geneua had battered it the yere before, right againſt the other fort. Which done, he entred into the balliage of Gez, wher without reſiſtance, he tooke both the towne and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel: meane time, pacifiyng the Lords of Berne, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to make a fort at Verſoy, therby to hinder on that ſide the paſſage to Geneua, both by water &amp; by land.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A deſcription of the fort of Verſoy.</head>
               <p>This Verſoy is a little Bourg, conteining in it about ſeuentie houſes, hauing Geneua, (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant 2. French leagues) on the South part, the balliage of <hi>Thonon</hi> &amp; the Lacque of the Eaſt part, mount Zura
<pb facs="tcp:3165:10"/>
on the weſt part, &amp; the country of Vaut on the North part. It is ſcituated on the ſide of the Lake, hauing two gates, and a riuer iſſuing out of the mountains named Verſoy, the which by one of her braunches runneth through the midſt of the bourg, &amp; by the other paſſeth along before the gate which goeth vnto Geneua, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, there is the proportion of an olde caſtle, the wals whereof are yet ſtanding, with an high tower. This place the Duke perceiuing to bee verie fit to bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle thoſe of Geneua, reſolued to fortifie the ſame, which he did with great dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: his armie being lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged therabout, the better to bring it to paſſe: firſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cauſed the entries and feeble places to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricadoed, the old caſtle to be new repaired, &amp; a trench towards the Weſt in forme of a ſpur, hee ſtopped the breches, erecting a platforme on the ſide of the Lake, whereon were placed two field peeces, which hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the paſſage of all barkes &amp; gallies that would paſſe vp vnto Geneua, in ſuch ſorte, that by daie it was not poſſible without great danger to paſſe by water vnto the towne (notwithſtanding that the Lake is halfe a league broad in that place) by reaſon the peeces caried ſo farre, and that the ſtreame (whereby the boats were carried vp) ran principally in the midſt of the Lake, which fort being made, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the cuſtodie ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of to the baron of de la Sarra, eſteemed for one of the beſt ſouldiers of Sauoy, leauing with him 600. choſen ſoldiers, vnder the leading of old Captains, to keep &amp; defend the ſame, furniſhing them with all manner of munition for warre and victuals in great abundance: and beſides the two field peeees placed on the water ſide, he cauſed foure Canons to bee brought thether,
<pb facs="tcp:3165:11"/>
with great quantitie of bullets and pouder. Hee lefte likewiſe with the ſaid Baron ſeuentie gally ſlaues, both Turkes and Chriſtians, (which had ſerued in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the fort of Sonzy) for to make an end and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that which was begun at Verſoy, where they to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Countrie men and ſome ſouldiers, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch diligence, and made ſo great expedition, that in ſhort time the ſayde Bourg became meruaylous ſtrong, and by them was named Saint <hi>Maurice:</hi> which puffed the Duke vp with ſuch pride &amp; aſſurance, that he called his Canons the keyes of Geneua, and at his departure he deſired the ſaid Baron verie earneſtly to doe his indeuour. This done, in the moneth of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1589, for that there happened diuerſe newe and ſtrange diſeaſes in his armie, hee retired with his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers (in verie pittifull &amp; languiſhing eſtate) vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy, and from thence vnto Piemont. All this he did in the moneths of Iune, July, Auguſt, September &amp; Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober, with extreame deſolation of all the Countrie round about Geneua, ſpecially in the balliages of Gez and Ternier, wherein hee cauſed all actes of hoſtilitie to bee vſed and exerciſed againſt his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, for that the ſeconde daie of September hee cauſed the frontiers of Colonges to be burnt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, which was done and executed by the gariſon of the Cluze, wherein they murthered, maſſacred, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flouted, drowned and hanged of men, women and children to the numder of one hundreth and two and twentith perſons well knowen, beſides ſuch as were not found, and remaine as yet vnknowen: and vpon the thirteenth daie of September he being in the balliage of Gez, the daie before, his troups marching
<pb facs="tcp:3165:11"/>
vnto Croſet, tooke one Gead Barbir Miniſter of the word of God in the ſayd pariſh, beeing about the age of 70. yeares, whoſe feete they cloue in two, and ſetting him verie contemptuouſlie vpon an Aſſe, his face towardes the Aſſes taile: They led him in ſuche manner before the Duke himſelfe, in whoſe preſence hee affirmed that hee had preached nothing but the truth: and wherein he was fully determined to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vntill his end, wherevpon they brought him back againe, &amp; caſt him vpon a litle ſtraw before his houſe, where hee gaue vp his ghoſt and died, a ſpoile beeing made of all his goods and ſubſtance: in the which vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage they likewiſe ſpoiled, murthered, and deſtroyed eight other poore and aged perſons: whereof the names are exſtant to be ſeene. And about the fiftenth of the ſame moneth, the ſaid troupes being in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of Gez, Diuonne, Villars, Plaus, Aberoz, and Petigny, they maſſacred, burnt, and deſtroyed by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers torments, to the number of one and twenty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, with fourteene houſes which they burnt in the parriſh of Villars, beſides all theſe herein ſpecified, &amp; manye other whiche are not as yet come to light or knowen. It were hard to number the women and Maids that were forced and deflowred by them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie reſpect of age: for that many graue Matrons, who were to bee reuerenced for their yeares, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Maiden children to be reſpected for their tender age, could haue no aſſurance againſt the rapes, violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and furies, of theſe inraged Diuels incarnate. For it may bee ſaid truly, that fewe of all the Women or Maides that fell into their hands, haue hardly eſcaped diſhoneſting, and ſuch as reſiſted their violence, in ſo
<pb facs="tcp:3165:12"/>
much as that they could not force them) were maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred: and (which is a thing moſt execrable, wherof the like hath not bene heard of among the barbarous Scythians.) Some women being hurt to death, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to yeeld vp their ghoſts, (thoſe villains deſirous to enioy their companies) departed out of their liues, as they lay vnder them. They likewiſe burnt diuers Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and manie Farmes, neere the forte of Cluze, ſo that in a manner, they left deſſolate, and made waſte the moſt part of all the Villages thereabouts, depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the Countrie by their barbarous and inhumain cruelties. By which murthers it may be gathered, how manie Orphants and fatherleſſe Children they haue made, liuing in great miſerie and pouertie, howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Families ruined and ſubuerted, and how manie honeſt houſes impoueriſhed and beggered. The Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron de la Sarra in the meane time lay not ſtill, but day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie skermiſhed, and beat the boats which paſſed vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Geneua, and had diuers times bragged and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, aſwell by his Letters which were intercepted by thoſe of Geneua, as by worde of mouth, that in ſhort ſpace he would force the town to yeeld to the Duke. They of Geneua, perceiuing themſelues abandoned of all men, conſidering likewiſe and feeling very wel, that Verſoy, remaining in that eſtate, dailie fortifieng it ſelfe, would be ſuch a yoake vnto them, that in the end, it would bee their vtter ouerthrowe and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concluded to vſe ſome meanes (by Gods helpe) wherby they might breake the ſame, and after diuers ſmall attempts, (procuring an aſſurance rather then a feare vnto the enemie,) The ſeuenth of Nouember, 1589. keeping their gates ſhut, that no man might
<pb facs="tcp:3165:12"/>
paſſe out: In the Euening they cauſed their ſmall troupes to bee aſſembled, in number about fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred footmen, with ſome hundreth and fiftie volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Souldiers: two companies of Argoletiers, and two of Lances, vnder the conduct of the Lord of Lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bignie, (commanding the ſayd troupes, in the behalfe of the moſt chriſtian King, together with diuers wiſe and expert Captains,) making their praiers vnto God with a full deliberation: about ten of the clocke in the night, iſſued forth of Geneua, cariyng with them cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Lathers, and peeces of woode, thereby to paſſe the riuer, within halfe a league of Verſoy. Not long before their iſſuing foorth, there appeared in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a great white circle which ſhone very bright, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the which followed certaine fierie Pillers, whereat thoſe of Verſoy were aſtoniſhed, and being in a feare, ſayd that they of Geneua would come and viſit them. But becauſe they had beene in armes all Thurſdaie at night, hauing watched vntill two of the clocke after midnight: betweene Fridaie and Saturdaie, the moſt part layed them ſelues downe to ſleepe: In the meane time, thoſe of Geneua marched forwards, and on Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turdaie after midnight paſſed the riuer, cloſe by a mill without any reſiſtaunce, comming about two of the clocke before Verſoy, where hauing receiued a briefe inſtruction from their Generall, they deuided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into four parts, the greateſt part of the footmen went towards the gate, opening vpon the countrey of Vaut, there to vſe their engine which they had purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlie brought with them, and the moſt part of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goletiers, and Lances, made a halt vppon the waies to the fort, part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſcending on foot, wer ordained
<pb facs="tcp:3165:13"/>
ſome to go vnto the ſcaling of the fort, &amp; the reſt (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeuenteene in number) followed a peiſaunt, who with a Leauer on his ſhoulder, led them very quietlie, and expertlye betweene the Bourg and the Lacque, where he brought them vnto a certaine eaſie paſſage, beeing the entrie (through a little lane or ſtreat) into the fort, he himſelfe ſhewing them the way, mounted firſt vppe, incouraged thoſe that followed him to doe the like, which being perceiued by the ſenturell, they ſone preuented by killing him: that done, thoſe ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teen armed men, each man hauing a Partiſan or cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telas in his hand, entred into Verſoy, where they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to make a marueilous boucherie of the Dukes ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, hauing ſupprized them in Peir, Corps de garde. Which certaine Captaines hearing, awaked, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to make reſiſtance, but being ſlaine, as the Baron thought to haue ioyned vnto them with the reſt of his troupes: they of Geneua, with their engine forced the gate of Copet, perſuing the exploit already begun by the ſeuenteen men aforſaid. Thoſe likewiſe which ſcaled the walles, entred at the ſame inſtant. But as in ſpeedie executions, it is impoſſible for men to ſee into all places at once, and that againſt all hope, the place was ſo ſodainelie wonne, (daye as yet not appearing) The Baron, with the reſt of his Souldiers, and part of his ſlaues, found meanes with ſpeed to enter into the Caſtell, wherein there ſtoode two Tentes, the Dukes 4. Canons, and great ſtore of warlike munition: but the victuals wer within the bourg which was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie taken, and almoſt three hundreth Sauoyans, Pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montiſians, and Italians, remaining dead in the place and in the houſes, not accounting ſuch as were burnt,
<pb facs="tcp:3165:13"/>
with others ſore wounded, which ſaued them ſelues by night, (leaping ouer the walles) and ſo gotte vnto the Caſtell of Baſtie, and of Gez, about a league and a halfe diſtant from thence, wherein the Duke held ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. The Barron, who had diuers times threatened thoſe of Geneua, that he would conſtrain them by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, with halters about their neckes, to kneele before the Duke, and ſubmit them ſelues vnto him, then found him ſelfe to be incloſed with his Souldiers, for the moſt part being in their doublets and hoaſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either bread, wine, or water: yet neuertheleſſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of neceſſitie a virtue, to aſtoniſh the victors, and mooue the Gariſons about him, as Thonon, Bonne, Sonzie, and Gez, to come vnto his aid and aſſiſtance, as alſo to haſten the Lorde of Sonnas, not farre from thence, with foure or fiue Cornets of Lances, (for the Duke had promiſed him by letter, that he ſhould want no ſuccours:) began moſt furiouſlie to thunder with his Canons, (their bullets waieng ſeuentene pounds) againſt the houſes of Verſoy, which hee continued vntill three of the clock in the Euening, in which time he did litle or nothing at al indomage thoſe of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, which had meanes to chuſe ſuche places for their ſafegard, as were out of the force of his battery. They loſt in all foure or fiue Soldiers, and about ſixteene or eighteene hurt, and thoſe almoſt all by their own fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. The Baron that day hauing diſcharged at the leaſt 35. or 40. ſhot, yet ceaſed not to doe the like all the next day being ſonday, (expecting his ſuccours, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thoſe of Gex had made him a ſigne,) and hurt with Musket ſhot ſuch as diſcouered themſelues. But in the Euening, the water being cut from him, whereof he,
<pb facs="tcp:3165:14"/>
and his began to haue want: no ſuccours appearing, he deſired a treatie of compoſition and yeelding vp, which was granted vnto him, and that more graciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlie, then either he or his, had anie waies deſerued, by reaſon of their inſolencies committed, whereof the Hiſtorie at large can well declare and ſhew forth: for they were ſuffered to depart, with ſuch Armes as they had, their matches not lighted, their Drumbs at their backes, two Enſignes wrapped vp, with all their bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage light inough for them to carie: in which maner, they were ſafe conducted vnto Gez, being in number about 200. men, in verie poore eſtate, and altogether aſtoniſhed, to haue bin ſo rudelie awaked and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to receiue the ſame intertainment, which they threatned to giue vnto thoſe of Geneua. The foure Canons, and the two other of the Dukes peeces, were drawn vnto Geneua, with fiftie barrels of powder, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Iron bullets, and great quantitie of Lead, as alſo the remainder of their meal, wherof the ſoldiers made great waſte, for that at the taking thereof, it was more then 200. Quintals: They likewiſe brought awaie with them two Enſignes, and all the Gally-ſlaues, to the number of three-ſcore and ten, wherof the Lords permitted ſome to depart where they would, the reſt willingly ſtaieng there, (being curteouſlie vſed) were imployed in ſuch ſeruice of their wars as neede requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The fort of Verſoy was ſoone after pulled down, and raced to the ground, the wals of the Caſtle ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, the Tower vndermined and ouerwhelmed, and the moſt part of the houſes burnt, thereby taking all meanes from them, for euer after that to fortifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in that place: Of the which yoake, the towne of
<pb facs="tcp:3165:14"/>
Geneua beeing freed, (yeelding thankes vnto God,) they found themſelues to be greatlie eaſed, by reaſon that victuals began in great ſtore and aboundance to be brought thither out of the Countrey of Vaut, and ſo hath continued euer ſince, their nauigation beeing free vntill this preſent, God bee thanked. This done, they tooke diuerſe other places about them, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verie much, they threw downe diuers brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and caſtles. And in the yeere 1590. hauing ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen the Baron of Ermanſſe, taken the towne of Gez, &amp; beaten down the caſtle, where the Duke loſt a great number of ſouldiers, they troubled the Dukes gariſons in diuerſe places: at the laſt they perceiuing and conſidering the ſcituation of the place of Cluſe to be verie ſtrong, and that it would bee a meanes to bridle their towne &amp; keepe it in ſubiection (although, they eſteemed it but loſt labour anie more to aſſaile ſo difficult a place as that was to be wonne, as alſo being wonne, of ſo great and dangerous defence vnto ſuch as are not maiſters of the field, and ſpecially on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the riuer of Rhoſne: although at other times they had determined not to enterpriſe the ſame) occaſion then being offered to thinke thereon, they tooke the matter vpon them in maner follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. About halfe a league from that fort on Geneua ſide, there ſtandeth a little caſtle ſomewhat ſtrong, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Pierre, within the which a Sauoyan called the Lord of Arſene, held a gariſon of fortie or fiftie ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, which daily iſſuing forth, ſpoiled and waſted the poore country men inhabiting in the balliage of Gez, and ſpecially ſuch as dwelt in the villages that were appertaining vnto the ſeigniorie of GENEVA.
<pb facs="tcp:3165:15"/>
with them likewiſe: there iſſued ordinarily out of the Cluze, about twentie Souldiers, who ſpared neither man nor woman, but violated both women and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, committing infinite other extortions. The Lord of Lurbigny, and thoſe of Geneua, (hauing taken and throwne downe the Caſtle of Gez, with other places anoying their towne,) ſeeing the inſolencies of thoſe of Berne, (which thought them ſelues out of feare, by reaſon of the diſtance between them and Geneua, &amp; truſting to their aid when time ſhuld ſerue,) determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to abate their pride. To the which end, they tooke with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 2. of the Canons which they had taken from the Duke at Verſoy, &amp; two other field peeces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, they ment with all ſpeede to batter the ſaid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. And on Thurſdaie the 16. of Aprill 1590. they ſent a troupe of fortie or fiftie Argoletiers before to diſcouer the place, and to ſhewe themſelues vnto the enemie: the ſame day there were about twentie eight or thirtie Harquebuſiers iſſued foorth of the Cluze, and running as farre as the village of Farges, (a good league diſtant from their fort, towards Geneua:) they tooke downe the Bell out of the ſteeple, and carried it with them, but in the end, it coſt them verie deare: for that they were no ſooner departed from thence, but the Argolatiers of Geneua arriued at Farges, and vnderſtanding what had happened vnto the Village, preſentlie made after, and hauing ouer taken them, within a Musket ſhot of the Caſtle of Pierie, ſet vpon them, and entring among men, ouer-threw them all: of whome, they ſlewe about fiue or ſixe and twentie, without any domage or loſſe vnto themſelues, onely that the Sargeaunt of their Companie was hurt in the
<pb facs="tcp:3165:15"/>
Arme, (whereof, neuertheleſſe he died not,) and the Captaines horſe ſlaine vnder him. The Lorde of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſene, and thoſe of Pierre made a ſhow as though they would haue ſuccoured their companions, but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution being ſo ſpeedilie done, and they perceiuing that the Argoletiers made towardes them, entered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into their fort, wherein they were preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed by thoſe of Geneua, and vpon Saturday after, without anie reſiſtance, yeelded vp the Caſtle vppon compoſition, heerevpon, the Lord of Lurbigny and thoſe of Geneua, finding ſo good an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſent three companies of their Souldiers, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the Cluze, to breake the bridges, and to keepe certaine paſſages, that thereby, thoſe of the Cluze might not bee aided with freſh men from the Gariſons lying about them. The Captaine within the ſame, beeing a Piemontois, with about a thirtie Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers more, hauing intelligence of the ouerthrowe of his men, which they thought had beene taken priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, was much amazed: yet in the end after great grief (by reaſon he had loſt the beſt Souldiers he had) hee determined to ſtand in defence, expecting aide from other places, preſentlie after the yeelding vp of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Pierre: The peeces were drawne beyond Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, for to batter the two fortes, and men were ſent vp vpon the mountaines, not onelie to keepe the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, but alſo to pull great ſtones out of the rocke, and to roule them down vpon the enemie within the fort, with the which, and with their canon, hauing broken the walles, ouerthrewe their incloſure and barica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, or platforme before the Rauelin. On Saturday the 19. of Aprill, the ſaid Rauelin was taken by thoſe of Geneua:
<pb facs="tcp:3165:16"/>
Notwithſtanding the furious reſiſtaunce of the fort beſeiged, and the Musketiers which ſhotte out of the fort of Saint Victore, and down from of the hill of Wache. The next day, thoſe of Geneua hauing got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnderneath the foot of the fort, ceaſed not to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt and greeue the Souldiers in the ſame with engins, Miners, and artificiall fiers of diuers ſorts, and that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie often: They within hauing gotten into the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt places of their fort, vpon whome, thoſe of Geneua threw &amp; rouled down gret ſtones from of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, which indomaged and hurt them very ſore, and in the end, would haue ſpoiled them altogether, from beneath, they made a great ſmoke which aſcended vp into the fort, deuiſing al meanes they could to plague them within, to incourage the aſſieged: Thoſe of the fort of Wache cried vnto them, courage, courage, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring them that their aid approched, as in truth it did and that on all ſides of the mountaines, and ſpeciallie on ſonday at night, the enemy made great ſignes and ſhowes of fire vnto thoſe that were beſieged: this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the Lorde of Lurbignie peceiuing his ſmal troups (although they were but hardly furniſhed of victuals) to increaſe in courage, and to be earneſtly bent vnto the fight, reſolued to aſſay al means poſſible wherby he might force the fort, by mining, by throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down ſtones from the mountaines, and with fire, wherevpon on monday at night, hee cauſed a mine to be made with great diligence at the foot of the tower. They within hearing a noiſe therof, &amp; hauing aſſaied (but all in vaine) to driue the miners from their place, which wrought out of their danger, the better to find out the mine, they fained to parle for an accord, but
<pb facs="tcp:3165:16"/>
for that in place of making a compoſition, the captain began to ſpeake very high and proudly: The Lord of Lurbigny cauſed him quickly to retire, &amp; therewith continued the mine: whereat they within, required him to ſurſeaſe, promiſing him, that if their ſuccours did not come vnto them the next day within an hour after the appearing of the daye, that then they woulde yeeld vp the place, and depart with their armes &amp; ſuch neceſſaries as they had, which was granted vnto them. Meane time, the Sauoyan forces were aſſembled with great diligence from al places, &amp; vpon monday the 20 of April, came vnto Chaſtillon in Michaille, within 2. leagues of the fort, marching towardes the ſame, but the craggines of the waie which they had marched, had ſo wearied their footmen, that they were conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to lie all that night within a league of the Cluze. On tuſdaie earlie in the morning they entred into the field, being in number about 1500. men, &amp; were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by their leaders, to deuide and raunge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into fiue Squadrons: whereof, one ſhould take the way, leading along the riuer of Rhoſne, the ſecond ſhould goe cloſe vnder the mountaine: (Theſe two were Lanciers, Piſtoletiers, and Petronels al horſmen) and the other three Squadrons al footmen with mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions, ſhould march through the plaine, leading right vpon Longeray, where they hoped to incloſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the footmen of Geneua, who hauing diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered their forces by litle and litle began to retire, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelues to weak for their enemies, not hauing any horſmen to defend them. The Sauoyans, hauing ſent forth 2 ſpies to diſcouer their enemy, &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies of Geneua began to diſlodge,
<pb facs="tcp:3165:17"/>
made haſt after them with a great noiſe and out-crie. While this happened, the time appointed for the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp of the fort was now expired, and the Lord of Lurbigny, who had made the compoſition, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the enemies approch, made a great noiſe with drums and trumpets, to the ende that the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the fort ſhould not heare the cries and ſhouts which thoſe within the fort of Wache made at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching of their aide: and therewithall wrought ſo ſpeedily, that hee cauſed the Captaine and eight and twenty ſouldiers which he had left him, with two wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and fiue or ſixe of the Country men, which they had taken priſoners, to iſſue out of the fort, &amp; in their place cauſed certaine pikes and muskets to enter in &amp; take poſſeſſion of the ſame, ſpeedily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueying the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and his ſouldiers (all wearied, and parte hurt as they were) ſome part on their waie. At the ſame time that the fort was yeelded vp, the Sauoyans began in great number to come downe vnto the fort, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the retreate of three companies of Geneua, began to ſpread themſelues abroade, as they thought beſt, making their account that not one of them ſhuld eſcape their hands, ſpecially truſting to the ſuccour of the fort, which they as yet eſteemed to bee theirs, and whereof the Duke of Sauoy made ſo much account, that he bragged, that with the ſame Fort &amp; thirty men he had driuen backe, and coulde bridle a whole armie of Frenchmen and Switſers. Beeing thus diſperſed, they began verie boldly to diſcharge againſt thoſe of Geneua, who hauing by good happe, recouered the ſide of a hill, made them ſo hard an anſwere, that their footmen in the end were conſtrained to retire, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:3165:17"/>
ranged in order, they began a freſh charge, meane time that a great troup of their horſe men, with certain armed men on foote approched verie neere vnto the fort, calling the Captain by his name, &amp; diſplaied one of their banderols, hauing a red croſſe vpon the ſame, but the anſwere that they receiued was with musket ſhot, which ouerthrew diuers of them, beſides a great peece which ſo played vpon them, that it ſlew diuerſe of their horſe men, wherewith the foot men of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua which were on the one ſide, gaue them ſuch a freſh charge, that they retired with al ſpeed, &amp; being a good diſtance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fort (perceiuing that they had ſtaide ouer-long) in as good order as they could, they tooke the waie leading vnto the mountaine, leauing diuerſe of their companie dead in the place, and all the wayes couered with their bloud, in ſuch manner, that it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a butcherie or ſlaughter of cattell. The Lorde of Lurbigny and thoſe of Geneua were not a little raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with admiration, not onely to ſee themſelues ſo ſoone to be deliuered of their enimies, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie loſſe but onely three men ſlaine, &amp; foure or fiue hurt, but alſo that they were with ſuch ſpeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come maſters of the ſtrongeſt fort in all that countrie, for the which both there and within the town of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua they yelded heartie thanks vnto God: in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging wherof they loſt about ſeuen or eight men, but preſently after they perceiuing that the ſayde place could not verie well be holden by them, not hauing ſufficient forces to keep &amp; defend ſo many paſſages &amp; waies, as well on the one ſide as the other of the fort &amp; of the riuer of Rhoſne, cauſed the fort of Cluſe to bee blowen vp with pouder, which within certain weekes
<pb facs="tcp:3165:18"/>
after, was again ceaſed vpon by the Dukes forces, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be made ſomwhat longer, and aſmuch vnder the couert of the mountaine as he cold deuiſe: but yet in ſuch maner, that whoſoeuer hath the plaine on that ſide which butteth vpon Longeray and the Wache, maye eaſily compell them within the fort to abandon the ſame. The Dukes gariſons lying in Foſſigny, being moued with the good ſucceſſe of thoſe of Geneua, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 20. of May, and the 22. of April 1590. aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled themſelues togeather, and entred into diuers vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages on that ſide within a league of Geneua, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto their maiſter, where they moſt furiouſly and in great rage fell vpon the poore Countrey men: whereof they ſlewe a great number, not ſparing anie one, no not the women great with childe, nor yet litle children, for that they ſlew, murthered, and deſtroied by diuers torments, to the number of 62. perſons. On the other ſide, the Duke againe hauing taken, &amp; new built the Forte of Cluze, vnder the conduct of the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard of Sauoy, ſent an armie of 5. or 6. thouſand men into the balliage of Gez, which armie in the moneth of Iune, after they had ſlaine about 250. men of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, made a moſt horrible waſte &amp; deſtruction through out all the balliage, ſlaying ſuch of the Countrie men as they found, to the number of 27. perſons, whoſe names are recorded, committing ſuch villanies as are not to be rehearſed, and before their departure, burnt more then 60. good villages. On the ſide of Ternier, in the yere 1589. about the month of Iune, they made a fort (in a village named Sonzy,) calling the ſame S. Katherines fort, wherein the Duke left his great ſhot, wherewith, in fewe moneths, hee threatned to batter Geneua. The gariſon of this fort, hath ruinated &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the moſt part of thoſe villages, which at this
<pb facs="tcp:3165:18"/>
day are not inhabited: there remaineth onelie the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liags of Thonon, wherein there are ſixe or ſeuen ſcore villages, which the baron of Ermanſſe, and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies do by little and litle ſpoile and deſtroy, attending the comming of the Spaniards, Piemontoiſians, and other of the Dukes troupes, to ſet them all on fire, as they haue doone the reſt, following their pretended reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is, to make a deſert within ſix leagues round about Geneua, if otherwiſe they can not bring their purpoſe about, to get the town into their hands. Thus, one of the moſt faire, and fertile litle countries of Europe, hath in the ſpace of eighteene monethes, bene fourraged and ſpoiled by their owne Lord: and yet, all this notwithſtanding, thoſe of Geneua, in the middeſt of ſo many diſcommodities, haue continued without ſpoiling, being ſuſteined by a ſpeciall fauour from God himſelfe, and aided by certaine friendes, both far and neere, ſpeciallie the moſt Chriſtian king, who in diuers ſorts, accompanied with good effects, hath ſhewen a moſt great affection towads them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let this ſuffice you (gentle reader) as a ſcantling or ſmall proportion of one of the moſt memorable Hiſtories of our age, vntill ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe God to giue the meanes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome others which thinke thereon, &amp; whoſe memories may ſerue them, to collect and gather it in order more at large, to the end, that now you your ſelues, and your poſteritie after you, may ſee and behold the wonders and miracles of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God. Vnto whom be all honor, praiſe, and glory, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of Geneua, as vnto him onelie it appertaineth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Written at ſuch time as the troupes of Geneua, aſsiſted by thoſe of the moſt Chriſtian king, ouerthrew three cornets of Spaniſh and Neapolitane horſemen, belonging vnto the Duke, and therewith tooke the ſtrong caſtle of Buring in Foſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigny.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
